A Guide to the Papers of David Cron Yalden-Thomson 1949-1989
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Papers of David Cron Yalden-Thomson 1949-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12797
This collection consists of 1,312 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift to the library from Mr. Yalden-Thomson, and bears no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mr. David Cron Yalden-Thomson was born on 1919 March 12, Budport, Dorset, England. He studied at the Royal Naval College in Dartmouth (1932-1935), and saw military service in East Africa and in the Royal Canadian Air Force during World War II. After earning a B.A. with Honors and an M.A. from Queens College, Oxford, Mr. Yalden-Thomson studied and lectured at McGill University until receiving a Ph.D. in Philosophy in 1948. He was then appointed an Assistant Professor of Philosophy at the University of Virginia in September 1949, and in 1952 became an Associate Professor; took a leave of absence during the 1954-1955 term to accept a Ford Foundation Fellowship; served briefly as acting Chairman of the Department of Philosophy during 1960, and as the professor in charge of the University's Honors Program. His published works include Remarks about Philosophical Refutations and Hume: Theory of Knowledge. Mr. Yalden-Thomson is also a member of the Southern Society of Philosophy and Psychology. Please see the attached listing from The Directory of American Scholars for a more complete chronology.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of 1,312 items (1.7 shelf feet) and dates from 1949 to 1989. It contains the academic and personal papers of David Cron Yalden-Thomson of the Corcoran Department of Philosophy, including papers on the Corcoran Department of Philosophy, academic legislation, the Honors Program, The Society of Fellows, a draft biography of Ludwig Wittgenstein, notes on John Wisdom, Albert G.A. Balz, and Sir John Wheeler-Bennett.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection is filed in alphabetical order.
Organization
The collection is organized by subject.
Contents List
- Academic Legislation 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  (2 folders)
- Alderman Library 1951-1990 (Box 1)
- Balz, [Albert George Adam] 1949-1956 (Box 1)
- [Compensation and Finances] 1961-1974 (Box 1)
- Corcoran School of Philosophy 1949-1989 (Box 1)
- Committee on Curriculum 1970 Jul (Box 2)
- Data Sheets for Honors Students n.d. (Box 2)
- External Examiners 1967-1978 (Box 2)
- External Examiners 1967-1978 (Box 2)
- External Examiners (Honors) 1965-1974 (Box 2)
- Honors Applications 1976 (Box 2)
- Honors Book List n.d. (Box 2)
- Honors Committee on Special Programs 1977 (Box 2)
- Honors (Philosophy) -- General 1960-1978 (Box 2)
- Graduate Curriculum [1969] (Box 2)
- Gwathmey, [Allan Talbot] 1958-1966 (Box 2)
- Marshall Fellowship 1967 (Box 2)
- Law School Recommendations for Admissions 1967 (Box 2)
- "The Skipjack or Two-Masted Bateau 'Florine K. Gooch'"
- Southern Society for Philosophy and Psychology 1956-1975 (Box 2)
- Special Masters Degree Program 1965 (Box 2)
- Special Programs, Committee on 1979-1982 (Box 2)
- Student Recommendations, Woodrow Wilson Fellowships, et al 1952-1984 (Box 3)
- [University of Virginia - College of Arts and Sciences] 1957-1974 (Box 3)
- University of Virginia - [General Correspondence] 1949-1961 (Box 3)
- Wheeler-Bennett, Sir J. 1973-1975 (Box 3)
- John L. Williams Fund Correspondence 1957-1966 (Box 3)
- Notes on Wisdom, John 1954-1956 (Box 3)
- Draft of Ludwig Wittgenstein Biography of F.A. Hayek 1953 (Box 3)
- [Wittgenstein: The Philosophical Investigations] 1955 (Box 3)
- Lectures by John Wisdom 1957 (Box 4)